software engineering radio episode 76
special episode on the patterns journal
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to se radio this
is a special episode that we've briefly
spontaneously recorded at UPS la 2007
because we wanted to announce the new
patterns journal people always gave us
feedback that they're interested in
patterns and all the pattern community
and stuff so we thought why not announce
this new patterns journal on the podcast
the patterns journal is edited by Ralph
Johnson and James Noble and that's why
those two guys are the guests of this
episode why don't you guys introduce
yourself briefly and and and yeah well
give us a our listeners an idea of why
you're here so I'm Ralph Johnson I'm a
professor in the computer science
department the University of Illinois
and I've been with doing patterns things
for a long time I was one of the people
who wrote design patterns all right and
I've been to every plop I've been a
couple of euro plops couple chilly plops
never went to a koala plop or a sugar
loaf plop or haven't been to a Viking
plop sure what others is there's some in
the works that have started yet so I
haven't been to those either but the I
was at the mini plop that they had it
oops I this year so there's a lot of
different pattern events and that's
partly why we are starting the journal
mmm hi I'm the symbol formerly known as
James Noble and I'm professor of
software engineering at Victoria
University of Wellington in New Zealand
I've also obviously been working in
patterns for a while I shouldn't say
obviously but I have been working in
patents for a while along with other
things and have attended plops and
Europe hops which I just love in klosty
is a in cough boy area obviously in ESA
it's just a beautiful place and I was
involved in setting up and running the
koala plots in Australia and we're
hoping that there will be a koala plop
in New Zealand cool so the reason why we
kind of scheduled this special episode
quickly and like sneaked it in between
some of the other
episode was that there is this new
panelist channel going on well that's
right and this is something that the
hillside group the patins community have
been wanting to put together for a while
at least two years and so we're very
pleased that Springer Verlag publisher
of the world-famous in Heidelberg
lecture notes in computer science have
taken this journal on so so what's the
plan with this journal is it going to
publish the Proceedings of the
conference's or will it be somewhat
orthogonal it's somewhat orthogonal but
it's closely related in the sense that
the conference's will continue to have
their own proceedings but it's important
to for people who have never been to a
conference one of these conferences are
very quite different for something like
oops yeah because the attitude of the
program committee is to help the authors
to make good papers not to select good
papers out of the large number that are
submitted so the whole the whole event
is organized around these writers
workshops where authors are given a lot
of feedback from other authors from
attendees who typically are pretty
knowledgeable about patterns given a lot
of feedback and then they will leave the
conference and go off and work some more
on their papers and make them even
better
now the journal was meant to be the next
step in the publishing process so yeah
so you you had it published it up at a
plot but you're still working on it it's
a work in progress you're making it
better and better and then we'll come to
the journal you know the people really
in the patterns are going to like the
journal because they'll be able to see
you know latest things and but there
always be a lot of patterns there would
be on topics they won't be interested in
plenty of patterns of topics they are
interested in and you sort of select the
ones that that that are relevant to you
and ignore the rest but just like we buy
the books that are relevant to us ignore
the rest so it is a step beyond the
plops we're gonna have a lot more
reviewing one of the things we're gonna
try to do is get fraud and experts in
sorry they'll bring a paper on
object-oriented programming to plop you
can get a lot of people who are really
experts at object-oriented
but if you bring a paper on real-time
programming or avionics or all sorts of
stuff that people bring its we can't
tell you whether you're missing some
important idea because nobody there is
an expert on that we had some papers on
parallel programming that were brought
to plop in Illinois well we had some of
invited some of my professors and the
department who were experts on that to
actually come out coder there so we were
able to bring in some but that's that's
not what usually happens by that's from
it's something we recognize this is a
problem at the plops and people but we
want to have experts come from anything
we don't say it's only about object or
the pattern started and so that's tends
to be the sort of people who come to
plop so that's one of things we're gonna
do is try to bring in these content
experts from reviewing and we're gonna
have a lot higher standard of reviewing
we won't be quite so friendly as as the
plop see of those conferences are very
welcoming really trying to make
everybody feel comfortable and this is
if you're a first time off and you're
wondering work and I probably shall tell
you know it's much friendlier publish it
to go to a plop and have a paper there
then than your typical a conference I
can tell it from our own experience if I
look back at the stuff I submitted in 99
I guess well they were very but we're
gonna journals gonna be a bit more like
a journal and we're gonna have high
standards and we're gonna reject lots of
papers and just because you went to a
plop and and and it got through there
you know it may take you three or four
rounds before you get past the journal
review that's like I said we want ahead
it's the next stage and right again our
motive is the same we're trying to help
create great literature so our motive is
the same but now we're sort of expecting
the people you've gotten in you sort of
figured out a lot and so we're gonna
move to the next level now so do you
have to have a paper workshop that our
conference before you can submit it to
the journal or is that just a useful but
not mandatory thing to do now we've
that you have to have paperwork shopped
at not just anywhere but one of the one
of the serious hillside sponsor o'clock
conferences before you can have a before
you should submit your paper to a
journal and in fact if you're thinking
of submitting we're asking people to
tell us what was the latest plot where
the paper was workshopped
and and who was sort of running a
workshop workshop there and this is this
is not because we don't think that
there's good works being done on outside
plops and and there certainly are it's
because what the journal is about is
publishing and collecting and
recognizing the very best work that's
done in patterns for software and for
other things so somehow it takes over
the role of the plop D box of the five
books that have been there in a more
let's say fine granular and mouriak
regular that's what that's Ron I'm very
glad you mentioned that because of
course people such as everybody around
this table have had been an editor or
involved in the pop D book series but
for reasons of their own the publisher
of that series decided the series
couldn't really carry on sure and in a
lot of way it was a it was a funny thing
for that book series to be doing because
really what the patins Journal is doing
and will probably do better is what
those pop D books were doing they came
out once every two or three years so it
was an event it took two years to put a
talk about two years to produce so they
were always lagging behind stuff that
was actually going to the flops and
we're hoping that by setting up this
more regular venue where material
submitted to the journal rather material
accepted to the journal will be
available online and through ish
maneuver like website you will be able
to buy these books over amazon.com once
they come out so it's got to be
electronic the journal or will it be yes
it'll be printed it will be electronic
and print is important because one of
the things that the panel patterns
journal is explicitly setting out to do
is encourage academics now to actually
come around not only write patterns but
also write papers that talk about
patterns so for example one of the
questions that we always get about
patterns is where
can I find good patterns for doing X X
is finite state machines or whether X is
Ajax or whether X is websites and so one
of the things we're hoping if people
submit these things that will start
appearing in the patents Journal is a
guide to patterns about websites for
example yep can I keep my layout the
design the layout the white space that I
put into parents I mean parents have
always also been about nice literature
about writing nicely formatted nicely
looking well structured stuff will this
go away in to make it compatible to I
don't know the Ln C as felon CS does
have standards but we can fit into that
without too much trouble in fact one of
the highlights of artistry is working
within a set of constraints okay so we
talked about how to submit your first go
to a conference have your paper workshop
and then there is a separate submission
thing where I say this is where I've
been to the conference here is yes and
reading the journal works by going to
some kind of website the patterns
journal calm or where there will be a
website there also will be a printed
version so yeah they'll both be there
one of the things because of it being a
part of the lncs it's going to be in
libraries there's I don't know a
thousand libraries that subscribe to it
so it definitely it's archival
publication and doesn't depend just on
the web the hillside group has a pointer
to it too so you could go to the site
net and look up the journal hillside net
/t PLO P transactions on patent
languages of programming okay so to wrap
this thing up
is there any highlights that you might
have already planned for the first
couple of episodes anything you want to
point our listeners to explicit well we
have plans for things we're expecting to
frequently have special issues on on
topics what we're thinking is the first
special issue will be on pedagogical
pattern Wow cool when will the first
type the first episode when will the
first issue be available what's the plan
we're hoping to have
by next summer okay cool and then every
we are promising springer-verlag that we
will do at least one a year and we're
aiming for two a year but I think that
if we had more they would be happy to
give more because it doesn't cost them a
lot so if we had four or five a year if
we actually had good material for that
so and I'll just say that we are
especially interested in reviewers so
right if people will have a place if
they go the website will have a place a
people can contact us and tell us what
their expertise is and just to clarify
the review is not necessarily about the
pattern s of something so you don't if
you a pattern expert it's about subject
matter and we get beyond the pattern is
right and that's what you need to review
specifically because the pattern is kind
of can be reviewed by the prob
conference before it's submitted to the
right to the joint so one of the things
about patterns way back when was the
idea of building a handbook for software
architecture that there would be a
reference that would be on the shelf or
in the library that when and when a
practicing engineer needs to do
something that maybe they don't know how
to do but there sure has been done
before somewhere that they can go and
they can find out about now in almost
every other engineering discipline there
are these kind of handbooks not
everybody has them but you know they're
in libraries large engineering firms
have got these things and small
engineering consultancies you've got
access to them if you've worked with
other kinds of engineers whether it's
roading engineers whether it's
aeronautical engineers whatever all this
kind of information is available and
that was the dream of the patins
community when it first started and we
think that the transactions on pattern
languages of programming is the next
step in bringing that dream to reality
for software engineers next step is a
really important part of that because we
don't think that we're going to make
that happen just with with the journal
because you have to do the journals more
of a continuing this bottom-up of
producing a lot of pieces of that some
where someone's going to have to come
to a top down there have to be some
organization that take out the efforts
great easy great well
Grady's book is is another step along
there Franken Kevin's magnum opus we
call nineteen to twenty seven but
actually I think it's going to have to
be a group like you know the ACM or I
Triple E or Sam some international
organization that that responds or
something like that okay thank you very
much you both for being on the show
thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details